<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the sad and great persecution and martyrdom of the people of God, called Quakers, in New--England for the worshipping of God. Wherof 22 have been banished upon pain of death. 03 have been martyred. 03 have had their right-ears cut. 01 hath been burned in the hand with the letter H. 31 persons have received 650 stripes. 01 was beat while his body was like a jelly. Several were beat with pitched ropes. Five appeals made by them to England, were denied by the rulers of Boston. One thousand forty four pounds worth of goods hath been taken from them (being poor men) for meeting together in the fear of the Lord, and for keeping the commands of Christ. One now lyeth in iron-fetters, condemned to dye. Also, some considerations, presented to the King, which is in answer to a petition and address, which was presented unto him by the general court at Boston : subscribed by J. Endicot, the chief persecutor there; thinking thereby to cover themselves from the blood of the innocent.</title>
            <author>Burrough, Edward, 1634-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77941</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5994</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1086_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13926</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859579</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859579</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169368</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77941)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169368)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 161:E1086[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the sad and great persecution and martyrdom of the people of God, called Quakers, in New--England for the worshipping of God. Wherof 22 have been banished upon pain of death. 03 have been martyred. 03 have had their right-ears cut. 01 hath been burned in the hand with the letter H. 31 persons have received 650 stripes. 01 was beat while his body was like a jelly. Several were beat with pitched ropes. Five appeals made by them to England, were denied by the rulers of Boston. One thousand forty four pounds worth of goods hath been taken from them (being poor men) for meeting together in the fear of the Lord, and for keeping the commands of Christ. One now lyeth in iron-fetters, condemned to dye. Also, some considerations, presented to the King, which is in answer to a petition and address, which was presented unto him by the general court at Boston : subscribed by J. Endicot, the chief persecutor there; thinking thereby to cover themselves from the blood of the innocent.</title>
                  <author>Burrough, Edward, 1634-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Wilson, in Martins Le Grand,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1661]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: E.B., i.e. Edward Burrough.</note>
                  <note>Title page in red and black; the words "22 have been banished .. condemned to dye." are bracketed together.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March 30. 1661".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Quakers --  Persecutions --  New England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169368:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION Of the SAD and GREAT Perſecution and Martyrdom Of the People of God, called QUAKERS, in <hi>NEW-ENGLAND,</hi> for the Worſhipping of God.</p>
            <p>Wherof
<list>
                  <item>22 have been Baniſhed upon pain of Death.</item>
                  <item>03 have been MARTYRED.</item>
                  <item>03 have had their Right-Ears cut.</item>
                  <item>01 hath been burned in the Hand with the letter H</item>
                  <item>31 Perſons have received 650 Stripes.</item>
                  <item>01 was beat while his Body was like a jelly.</item>
                  <item>Several were beat with Pitched Ropes.</item>
                  <item>Five Appeals made by them to <hi>England,</hi> were denied by the Rulers of <hi>Boſton.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>One thouſand forty four pounds worth of Goods hath been taken from them (being poor men) for meeting together in the fear of the Lord, and for keeping th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Commands of Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>One now lyeth in I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on-fetters, condemned to dye.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>ALSO, Some CONSIDERATIONS, preſented to the KING, which is in <hi>Anſwer</hi> to a <hi>Petition</hi> and <hi>Addreſs,</hi> which was preſented unto Him by the General Court at <hi>Boſton:</hi> Subſcribed by <hi>J. Endicot,</hi> the chief Perſecutor there; thinking thereby to cover themſelves from the Blood of the Innocent.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gal. 4.29.</hi>
               </bibl> But as then, he that was born after the fleſh, perſecuted him that was born after the Spirit, even ſo it is now.</q>
            <q>
               <hi>God hath no reſpect to</hi> Cains Sacrifice, <hi>that killed his Brother about Religion.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Wilſon,</hi> in <hi>Martins Le Grand.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:169368:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:169368:2"/>
            <div type="considerations">
               <head>SOME CONSIDERATIONS Preſented unto the King of <hi>England, &amp;c.</hi> BEING Partly an <hi>Anſwer</hi> unto a <hi>Petition</hi> and <hi>Addreſſe</hi> of the Gen. Court of <hi>Boſton</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> preſented un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the King (as is ſaid) <hi>Feb.</hi> laſt, the 11th day.</head>
               <p>OH King, this my occaſion to preſent thee with theſe <hi>Conſiderations,</hi> is very urgent and of great neceſſity, even in the behalf of <hi>Innocent Blood;</hi> hoping that my Work will find ſuch favour with thee, as to induce thee to the reading and ſerious conſideration hereof: my occaſion is this, Becauſe of a Paper preſented to thee, called <hi>The humble Petition and Adreſſe of the General Court at</hi> Boſton <hi>in</hi> New-England: In which is contained <hi>divers Calumnies,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt <hi>Reproaches,</hi> palpable <hi>untruths,</hi> and malicious <hi>ſlanders,</hi> againſt an Innocent People, whom they ſcornfully call <hi>Quakers;</hi> whom, for the Name of Chriſts ſake, are made a Reproach through the world, and by theſe Petitioners, have been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted unto <hi>Baniſhment,</hi> and <hi>Death;</hi> it is hard to relate the <hi>Cruelties</hi> committed againſt theſe People, and acted upon them by <hi>theſe Petitioners;</hi> they have <hi>ſpoyled</hi> their Goods, <hi>impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned</hi> many of their Perſons, <hi>whipped them, cut off their Ears, burned</hi> them, yea, <hi>baniſhed</hi> and <hi>murdered them;</hi> and all this <hi>I aver</hi> and <hi>affirm</hi> before thee, O King, wholly <hi>unjuſtly</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſly,</hi> and without the Breach of any Juſt Law of God or Man; but only for and becauſe of <hi>Difference</hi> in <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> concerning <hi>Spiritual things,</hi> &amp; without any tranſgreſſion of the Law of God, or their own Laws; Saving that they made Laws againſt them, on purpoſe <hi>to ſpoil <hi>their Goods,</hi>
                  </hi> impriſon <hi>their Perſons,</hi> cut off <hi>their Ears,</hi> yea and <hi>kill them;</hi> which Laws were made by them, without any Power truly derived
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169368:3"/> from the lawful Authority of <hi>England, <hi>contrary to their Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ent.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now, O King, theſe ſame Men have preſented thee with a Petition, in which is aſſerted very many <hi>ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ream Reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> as I have ſaid, in <hi>contempt</hi> and <hi>deriſion</hi> of that People; and all this, as if thoſe People were guilty of heinous crimes, that it might appear to thee as if theſe Petitioners had done nothing but Juſtice in what they have done; and they ſeek to cover themſelves, and to hide their Wickedneſs before thee, in what they have unjuſtly acted; and this ſeems to be the current of ſome part of the ſame <hi>Petition,</hi> already preſented unto thee; like as if they had done no Evil, though they have <hi>uniuſtly ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, cut off Ears, whipped inhumanely,</hi> and <hi>taken away lives,</hi> as aforeſaid; and they would have thee believe they are <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> towards thee, and towards us; when as it is evident, as the Sun at Noon-day, that they are <hi>our perſecu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ors,</hi> and that they have <hi>unjuſtly perſecuted</hi> us <hi>unto death</hi> for the Name of Chriſt; and that alſo they are not unto thee as they hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally feign themſelves.</p>
               <p>And therefore, O King, for the clearing of our ſelves, and the Name of the Lord which we profeſs, and for the reproving of their bold and impudent Inſolencies, both in what they have already done to us, and now in ſeeking to cover themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee; and alſo, if there be any doubtfulneſs in thy heart of theſe matters, for theſe ends and cauſes, with reſpect to the <hi>Fear of God,</hi> and <hi>Honour to the King,</hi> I hereby preſume to <hi>purſue</hi> their ſaid <hi>Petition,</hi> even unto <hi>thy Court,</hi> and to wipe away the <hi>ſlanders</hi> and <hi>reproaches</hi> of Ungodly men, as much as poſſible; hoping hereby thou wilt receive due and juſt information in this matter of proceeding between us and them, that thy Juſt Judgment may be given accordingly.</p>
               <p>And I ſhall tranſcribe ſome few of their own words preſented to thee, and thereupon ſpread ſome few Conſiderations before thee alſo; and I pray God give thee an underſtanding to judge juſtly in this and <hi>all other caſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt thing that I note, is, Whereas they ſay, <hi>That they have choſen rather the pure Scripture-worſhip with a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in this poor remote Wilderneſs</hi> (to wit, <hi>New-England) among the Heathens, than the pleaſures of</hi> England, <hi>with ſubjection to the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169368:3"/> impoſition of the then ſo diſpoſed, and ſo far prevailing Hierarchy, which we could not do without an evil Conſciencee, &amp;c.</hi> ſay thay.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Conſiderations</hi> preſented to the King, upon theſe words, are divers.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Worſhip, Doctrine, Diſcipline</hi> and <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of the Church of <hi>New-England,</hi> is <hi>different</hi> and <hi>contrary,</hi> and not purely according unto the Scriptures, in the Adminiſtration of the Goſpel; nor in a pure Conſcience, purely guided by the Spirit of God, though they ſeem to juſtifie their own way and caſe before the King; and this may juſtly be made appear in his preſence, upon good occaſion; only at this time I aſſert the Caſe, and, if ever God gives opportunity, I may proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute it with <hi>Proofs</hi> and <hi>Evidences,</hi> and that to the great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof of <hi>the Church</hi> (ſo called) <hi>of New-England,</hi> who are not only in <hi>Doctrine, Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Converſation,</hi> contrary to the Scriptures, but <hi>impudent</hi> and too <hi>preſumptuous,</hi> to affirm their own <hi>Self-juſtification</hi> and <hi>Innocency</hi> before the King; when, as it is manifeſt, as the Day is from the Night, that the <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Members</hi> of the Church of <hi>New-England</hi> want the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> that gave forth the Scriptures, and follow <hi>the ſpirit <hi>of Perſecution, Violence</hi>
                  </hi> and <hi>Cruelty,</hi> and are void of a <hi>Good Conſcience</hi> both to God and Men: To prove this, there needs no greater Evidence than their own Deportment to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Harmleſs Quakers</hi> for theſe five years time, who, as I have ſaid, have <hi>ſpoiled</hi> their Goods, and <hi>impriſoned</hi> their Perſons, <hi>cut off</hi> their Ears, <hi>baniſhed them</hi> and Inhumanely <hi>put them to death;</hi> and all this only, becauſe of <hi>difference in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> in <hi>Religious matters;</hi> when as no manner of Evil could be charged upon them in the things <hi>between Man</hi> and <hi>Man:</hi> And if theſe be not works contrary to the Scriptures, and the Spirit that gave them forth, and contrary to a good Conſcience, I am yet ignorant, and muſt leave it to the Judgment of the King, before whom this matter is brought to receive his Judgment.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Let the King conſider, how they have <hi>ignorantly</hi> condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>themſelves</hi> in the ſame <hi>things,</hi> for which they have judged <hi>others;</hi> for while they ſeem to Complain of the <hi>Impoſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ions <hi>of the Biſhops,</hi>
                  </hi> which they ſtile <hi>prevailing Hierarchy;</hi> If it was
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169368:4"/> 
                  <hi>Tranſgreſſion</hi> in the <hi>Biſhops</hi> in dayes paſt, <hi>to impoſe</hi> upon <hi>theſe Petitioners,</hi> and to <hi>perſecute them</hi> for <hi>Non-Conformiſts,</hi> How much more <hi>are theſe men guilty</hi> of <hi>Impoſition</hi> and <hi>Perſecution of tender Conſciences?</hi> Nay, they have exceeded <hi>in the ſame Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion,</hi> and become <hi>ſeven-fold guilty of the ſins themſelves,</hi> which they Complain againſt <hi>in others;</hi> for they have gone further <hi>in Cruelty</hi> and <hi>Perſecution</hi> towards the innocent <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> than ever the <hi>Biſhops</hi> proceeded <hi>againſt them,</hi> even ſo far further, as the <hi>murthering</hi> of a <hi>Man</hi> is more than <hi>cutting</hi> off <hi>his Ear:</hi> and the Cauſe of the <hi>Quakers</hi> towards theſe <hi>Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> hath been as <hi>Innocent</hi> as ever theirs was towards the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh <hi>Hypocritical generation!</hi> who are Condemning <hi>of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> for that whereof <hi>themſelves <hi>are guilty;</hi>
                  </hi> and Impoſing <hi>upon others</hi> in a far higher degree than ever the <hi>Biſhops</hi> impoſed <hi>on them;</hi> witneſs their Law in <hi>New-England,</hi> which judgeth <hi>every man to pay</hi> 5 s. per day, <hi>who come not to their Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly,</hi> and <hi>impoſing Fines of</hi> 40 s. <hi>and</hi> 50 s. <hi>a piece on ſuch as meet together to Worſhip the Lord;</hi> which are evident Signes of an evil Conſcience, as themſelves ſpeak.</p>
               <p>The next thing that I note, upon which the King ought to Conſider, the Petitioners ſay, <hi>concerning the</hi> Quakers, <hi>open Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital Blaſphemers, open Seducers from the Glorious Trinity, the Lords Chriſt, the Bleſſed Goſpel, and from the Holy Scriptures as the Rule of Life, open Enemies to Government it ſelf, as Eſtabliſhed in the Hands of any but men of their own Principles, malignant Promoters of Doctrines directly tending to ſubvert both our Church and State.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By way of Anſwer <hi>to this,</hi> let the King Conſider:</p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>envious</hi> and <hi>deteſtable</hi> Spirit of <hi>maliciouſneſs</hi> of theſe <hi>Accuſers,</hi> and how <hi>vehement</hi> and <hi>fervent</hi> their perſecuting Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is drawn forth with reproachful tearms in the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, like as if they could not utter ſufficiently <hi>the Envy of their hearts,</hi> or, as if they <hi>wanted words</hi> to demonſtrate their <hi>malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> and <hi>devouring malice</hi> againſt that People, whom they in ſcorn call <hi>Quakers;</hi> and all this to preſent us <hi>odious</hi> and <hi>abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable</hi> before Thee, O King; I ſay but this of them unto thee, <hi>The Lord forgive them, <hi>if they have not ſinned unto death
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169368:4"/> and unpardonably;</hi>
                  </hi> I have no deſire <hi>of Revenge</hi> towards them, but I leave <hi>vengeance</hi> to the Lord, who will recompence in his ſeaſon; neither do I deſire <hi>to provoke</hi> or <hi>incenſe</hi> the King againſt them, only duty to God and the King teacheth me, and love conſtraineth me, and an abſolute neceſſity preſſeth much upon me, to ſpread our denyal of their <hi>bitter</hi> and <hi>malicious Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations</hi> againſt us, before the King, unto whom we are thus fowly accuſed: And I ſay, I am Confident, That the King hath better <hi>experience</hi> of us, than to believe theſe our <hi>malicious Accuſers;</hi> And I do Appeal to him, from the knowledge which he hath already of us, that he believes we are Innocent, and not guilty of thoſe things <hi>thus unjuſtly</hi> Charged upon us; and I queſtion not but he will rightly underſtand that theſe <hi>Accuſations</hi> are more <hi>out of Hatred</hi> and <hi>Envy againſt us,</hi> than out of deſire <hi>to benefit the King</hi> by ſuch preſentation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I do Teſtifie unto the King, and before the whole World, That we do <hi>profeſs</hi> and <hi>believe</hi> concerning the <hi>Father, Son</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> and the <hi>Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>bleſſed Goſpel,</hi> and the <hi>Holy Scriptures;</hi> I ſay, We do <hi>believe</hi> and make <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion</hi> in Truth and Righteouſneſs concerning all theſe things, and by our <hi>Doctrines</hi> and <hi>Inſtructions,</hi> do perſwade all People <hi>to believe,</hi> and not <hi>Seduce <hi>any</hi> from theſe Truths of the Goſpel:</hi> And this is known through theſe Kingdoms concerning us, though we ſtand now Accuſed falſly concerning theſe Matters before the King. But as for the Scriptures being the Rule of Life, We ſay, <hi>The Spirit of God that gave forth the Scriptures, <hi>is the Rule of Life and Faith unto the Saints,</hi> and leads not contrary, but according unto the Scriptures, in the beleif and practice of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the Scripture ſaith;</hi> and if theſe Petitioners did make the Scriptures the Rule of <hi>their Lives</hi> and <hi>Practices,</hi> for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial of which they here <hi>accuſe us,</hi> they would not have <hi>Cut off Ears, Baniſhed</hi> and <hi>put to Death</hi> for the Cauſe of Conſcience, which is contrary to the Scriptures, and proceedeth from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Spirit than that which gave forth the Scriptures.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Concerning <hi>Government,</hi> our <hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>Practices</hi> are known to many, and partly to the <hi>King;</hi> We are not Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies unto Government it ſelf, as theſe our Accuſers do charge us, but it is <hi>our Principle,</hi> and hath ever been, and is <hi>our Practice</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:169368:5"/> to be ſubject to whatſoever Government is ſet up over us, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>by doing</hi> or <hi>ſuffering;</hi> and neither <hi>to vilifie</hi> nor <hi>rebel</hi> againſt any <hi>Government</hi> or <hi>Governours,</hi> by any malicious <hi>Plots</hi> or <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances,</hi> but to walk <hi>in meekneſs</hi> and <hi>humility</hi> towards all, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſubject for Conſcience ſake, as I have ſaid, either by <hi>doing</hi> or <hi>ſuffering;</hi> and I doubt not but the King is ſufficiently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed hereof, and believeth this Teſtimony.</p>
               <p n="4">4. As for <hi>our Doctrines</hi> tending to ſubvert both Church and State, this is alſo <hi>a falſe Accuſation</hi> and <hi>Slander;</hi> for our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines are <hi>to convert,</hi> and not to <hi>ſubvert;</hi> even <hi>to Convert to God,</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> that men ſhould live in theſe things, and forſake all that which is contrary; and this effect our Doctrines have wrought in the World, as the Teſtimony of many Conſciences ſhall bear witneſs. Oh let the King Conſider of <hi>our Defence,</hi> as well as of our Enemies <hi>Charge,</hi> who have thought it not enough <hi>to whip,</hi> moſt cruelly <hi>baniſh, cut Ears,</hi> and put <hi>to death</hi> the Innocent, but muſt ſtill <hi>accuſe them falſly,</hi> and ſeek to cover themſelves <hi>by fawning</hi> and <hi>flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Addreſſes</hi> unto the King, like as if they had done no evil; when as <hi>the God of Heaven is witneſſe,</hi> to whom we can Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal, <hi>That our Brethren ſuffered the Tortures of ſhameful Death in</hi> New-England, (through their unjuſt Lawes and Sentences) <hi>as Saints and Servants of the living God, <hi>for the Name of Chriſt Jeſus, and for his Truth, which they held</hi> until Death, <hi>and not for evil-doing;</hi>
                  </hi> And the Executioners of theſe <hi>inhumane cruelcies</hi> ſeem ſo far from Repentance for their Evil doing, that they rather Juſtifie themſelves in what they have done, and ceaſe not <hi>to Smite,</hi> and <hi>Wound,</hi> and <hi>Reproach</hi> the Innocent, and that before the King, and that after <hi>they have martyred them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, Theſe Petitioners ſay, <hi>After all other means for a long time uſed in vain, We were at laſt conſtrained for our own Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> (ſay they) <hi>to paſs a Sentence of Baniſhment againſt them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Pain of Death, ſuch was their dangerous impetuous and deſperate Turbulency to Religion, and to the State Civil and Eccleſiaſtical, as that how unwilling ſoever, could it have been avoided, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, at leaſt in Conſcience both to God and Man, judged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, called for the Defence of all to keep the Paſſage with the Point
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169368:5"/> of the Sword held towards them; this could do no harm</hi> (ſay they) <hi>to them that would be warned thereby; their willingly ruſhing themſelves thereupon was their own act; and we with all humility conceive a Crime, bringing their blonds upon their own heads.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By way of Anſwer to this, let it be Conſidered:</p>
               <p n="1">1. What <hi>Means</hi> was for a long time uſed before they put them to Death, is <hi>ſhameful to mention;</hi> was it not by the means of <hi>cruel Whippings, Baniſhment, Impriſonment, cutting off Ears,</hi> and taking <hi>their Goods</hi> by violence? It is true, <hi>by this means</hi> the Petitioners dealt with the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and never by any <hi>Chriſtian-like means;</hi> for the very firſt of our Friends that ever came among them, <hi>they made them priſoners ere they came on ſhore,</hi> and <hi>inhumanely dealt with them,</hi> and <hi>baniſhed them;</hi> and this was the firſt and faireſt means that ever was uſed by them; which are not Goſpel-Means, nor the Way by which the Church of <hi>New-England</hi> ought to have proceeded; had our Friends been in Error, and ſuch, as they ſay of them, it had been their duty to have gained them <hi>by Love,</hi> by <hi>Mercy,</hi> and by <hi>long-ſuffering;</hi> theſe are the Weapons of the Spirit of God, which ought to be uſed towards them that are in Error, in order to the Converting of them from the Error; but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to this, the Magiſtrates and Church-Members of <hi>New-England</hi> took <hi>Cains</hi> Weapons, and dealt Cruelly, and not like Chriſtians, nor like ſober men, towards the Innocent; but their thus proceeding was in vain, as themſelves acknowledge, for notwithſtanding the Goſpel of Chriſt grew and encreaſed, and many were Converted to the Faith of Chriſt Jeſus, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>New-England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Let it be Conſidered, <hi>What their dangerous and deſpera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Turbulency was to States, Civil and Eccleſiaſtical?</hi> Did ever theſe poor People, <hi>whom they condemned</hi> and <hi>put to ſhameful death,</hi> lift up a hand againſt them, or appear in any <hi>Turbulent geſture</hi> towards them? Were they ever found wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h any Carnal Weapon about them? Or, what was their Crime, ſaving that they warned ſinners <hi>to Repent,</hi> and the ungodly <hi>to turn from his way?</hi> We appeal to the God of Heaven on their behalf, whom they <hi>have Martyred</hi> for the Name of Chriſt, That they had no other Offence to charge upon them, ſaving <hi>their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169368:6"/> Doctrines,</hi> and <hi>Practices,</hi> as Saints of the Moſt High God; and this is witneſſed by many of their Neighbours, though themſelves have hardened their hearts againſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof of Gods Witneſs; And we certainly believe it was their <hi>Malice</hi> and <hi>Envy</hi> that conſtrained them <hi>to paſſe Sentence of Death upon them,</hi> and not the <hi>Equity</hi> of either juſt Law of God or Man; for they deſerved not the merit <hi>of Death,</hi> ſuch was the Innocency of their Cauſe: and they are no more ſafe by the taking away the lives <hi>of our guiltleſſe Brethren,</hi> than they were before; no more ſafe, I ſay, but more liable to the Juſtice and Terrour of the Almighty, and to the Juſtice of the King, and the good Laws of <hi>England,</hi> for, and becauſe of their <hi>Barbarous Cruelties;</hi> but, as I have ſaid, we leave <hi>Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance to the Lord,</hi> and commit them to the Juſtice of Gods hand, which we doubt not but it will paſſe upon them in his day and ſeaſon.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whereas they would ſeem to <hi>extenuate</hi> their Crime <hi>of putting to ſhameful death the Lords ſervants,</hi> they tell the King, as if <hi>they only kept the Paſſage with the point of the ſword held towards them,</hi> as if <hi>they had no intention to hurt them,</hi> and this <hi>the Magiſtrate did both in Conſcience to God and man.</hi> I ſay, it is to be conſidered what occaſions were given them to ſtand in the paſſage with the point of the ſword towards this People, Was it for any cauſe on their part, but as aforeſaid, <hi>for repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their ſin,</hi> and <hi>crying againſt their wickedneſſe?</hi> when as their lives and converſations were harmleſs and innocent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them: I ſay, this was <hi>no juſt cauſe</hi> for the Magiſtrates to ſtand in the paſſage with the point of the ſword, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were unjuſt in ſo doing, if they had done no more, and proceeded in the way of Inſolent Uſurpers; for what rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon had they to ſtop the paſſage with the point of the ſword, for hindring of as good Subjects as themſelves to paſſe thorow the Kings Dominions? Is not this derogating from the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Authority of the King, for the ſubordinate Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of <hi>New-England</hi> to uſurp ſuch Authority over free-born People of <hi>England,</hi> as to prevent them from <hi>Egreſs</hi> and <hi>Regreſs</hi> in lawful occaſions in any part of the Kings Dominions? and I ſuppoſe this will be found <hi>contrary to their Patent</hi> and <hi>Preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:169368:6"/> delivered them by <hi>CHARLES the Firſt;</hi> even <hi>this ſtanding in the Paſſage with the point of the Sword</hi> toward the Innocent, and impoſing great Fines upon men that came to their Harbour to ſell their lawful Commodities; if they had but the name of <hi>Quakers,</hi> though no other thing could be charged againſt them, yet they were impoſed upon by <hi>Fines</hi> and <hi>Impriſonment,</hi> and the point of the ſword was held out againſt them; and all this, I ſuppoſe, is contrary to their Patent, and in <hi>Derogation</hi> and <hi>Diſhonour</hi> to KING <hi>CHARLES the Second.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. But to extenuate their own fact <hi>of put<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing to ſhameful death the Innocent,</hi> they charge their Death <hi>to be a wilfull ruſhing,</hi> and <hi>their Death was their own Act,</hi> and <hi>their Blood was upon their own Heads.</hi> Concerning which, let it be conſidered, they no more wilfully ruſhed upon their Death, neither is their Blood on their own heads, more than the <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles</hi> that were ſlain for the <hi>Teſtimony of Jeſus.</hi> But theſe Petitioners do plead: <hi>Theſe Quakers</hi> (ſo called) <hi>knew there was a Law pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed againſt them, Sentence of Baniſhment upon pain of Death; but they would not keep away, but came again, and run themſelves upon the Sword point:</hi> and after this manner of arguing they would make it appear <hi>their death</hi> was <hi>of themſelves,</hi> and <hi>their blood</hi> was on <hi>their own heads:</hi> But theſe poor <hi>Evaſions,</hi> and <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable Interpretations</hi> of their own <hi>Cruelties,</hi> ought not to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them from the Juſtice <hi>of God,</hi> nor from the Juſtice <hi>of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e King;</hi> for it's to be conſidered, that where God <hi>commands <hi>one thing,</hi>
                  </hi> and men <hi>another,</hi> God ought to <hi>be obeyed</hi> rather <hi>than men;</hi> and it is fully believed by us, that theſe Sufferers did not go into <hi>New-England</hi> in their <hi>own cauſe,</hi> but in <hi>Gods Cauſe,</hi> and in the Motion of <hi>his Holy Spirit,</hi> and in good Conſcience towards God: they did rather ſuffer the loſſe <hi>of their own lives</hi> for their obedience <hi>towards God,</hi> than to <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey him,</hi> to keep the Commandments <hi>of men;</hi> and this was the Apoſtles caſe, when they were commanded <hi>to preach <hi>no more</hi> in the Name of Jeſus,</hi> Did they at all obey it for fear of Man? And when the three Children were commanded to <hi>bow to the Image,</hi> did they do it for fear of Man? Or, if they had dyed for their diſobedience of the Kings Commandment,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169368:7"/> could it have been ſaid, <hi>That their Blood was upon their own heads,</hi> and <hi>that they ruſhed themſelves upon it?</hi> and this is in part the like caſe that our Friends ſuffered, under the Injuſtice of theſe Petitioners, who would now cover themſelves like men of guilty Conſciences; but the God of Heaven will let them know one day, and the King may juſtly do it, That <hi>the blood of our Brethren lyeth upon the heads of the Magiſtrates of New-England,</hi> and they are guilty <hi>of their cruel death;</hi> for they put them to death, <hi>not for any evil-doing</hi> between man and man, but <hi>for their obedience to God,</hi> and for good Conſcience ſake to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him.</p>
               <p>Again, The Petitioners ſay, <hi>The Quakers dyed not, becauſe of their other Crimes, how capital ſoever, but upon their ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>added Preſumptions, and incorrigible Contempt of Authority, breaking in upon us, notwithſtanding the Sentence of Baniſhment; had they not been reſtrained, there was too much cauſe to fear that we our ſelves ſhould quickly have dyed, or worſe; and they would not be reſtrained but by death: Nay, had they at laſt but promiſed to depart the Juriſdiction, and not to return without leave from Authority, we ſhould have been glad to have ſaid they ſhould not dye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In Anſwer to this, it is conſiderable,</p>
               <p n="1">1. What theſe other <hi>Capital Crimes</hi> were, which the Sufferers were guilty of; here is a ſecret Charge of <hi>Crimes,</hi> without <hi>nomination;</hi> and this is the part of <hi>Slanderers,</hi> to accuſe <hi>in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral,</hi> without <hi>particular proof;</hi> but this is ſtill to extenuate their own horrid fact, <hi>of putting the Innocent <hi>to death,</hi>
                  </hi> and that the King may believe better of them, than indeed he hath cauſe; and <hi>the ſuperadded Preſumption, and incorrigible Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Authority,</hi> What, was it any more, than that unjuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and without reaſon they commanded them <hi>to depart,</hi> or if they did not, <hi>they ſhould be put to death?</hi> when as no reaſon could poſſibly be rendred for ſuch Law and Commandment, but becauſe they were called <hi>Quakers,</hi> and were different in matters of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Judgment</hi> concerning <hi>Spiritual things;</hi> for, as I have ſaid, no <hi>Sedition, evil-dealing, Drunkenneſſe, Lying,</hi> nor any of theſe things could be charged againſt them, and therefore the Law and Commandment <hi>of Baniſhment</hi> was
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169368:7"/> unjuſt, and could not be <hi>actively obeyed by our Brethren;</hi> but they returned again, not in contempt of Lawful Authority, but as they were moved, and upon their occaſions, which was lawful and juſt in the ſight of God and Men, deporting themſelves harmleſly towards all people; and this is ſtiled, <hi>Superadded Preſumption, and Incorrigible Contempt of Authority:</hi> but they muſt needs put a <hi>Good Name</hi> upon their <hi>Bad Work,</hi> and render the Innocent as high Offenders, as excellency of ſpeech can demonſtrate.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There can be no <hi>just cauſe</hi> rendred, wherefore they ſhould fear our Brethren, except the Guiltineſs of their own Conſciences; for, as I have ſaid, they were never ſeen with any Sword or Staff amongſt them, nor any Carnal Weapon, nor ever held Deſigns of Miſchief; and for them thus wickedly to ſuggeſt unto the King, <hi>as if they would have killed them, or worſe,</hi> this is back-biting and ſlandering in the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and puniſhable by the Laws of God and Men; and it's true, them whom they <hi>have killed,</hi> are reſtrained, but the <hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>Practices</hi> of the <hi>Quakers</hi> (ſo called) hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into <hi>New-England,</hi> and paſſes thorow the Conſciences of people without reſtraint; and it's a ſhame for themſelves to mention, how all the <hi>Paſtors</hi> and the <hi>whole Church</hi> of <hi>Boſton</hi> overcame <hi>three Innocent perſons,</hi> and what weapons they over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came them by; not the weapons of the Spirit of God, but the weapons of <hi>Cruelty,</hi> and <hi>Hard-heartedneſs;</hi> even as <hi>Cain</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came <hi>Abel,</hi> and as the <hi>Jewes</hi> overcame <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and ſo did the <hi>Church of New-England</hi> overcome <hi>our Brethren:</hi> And this is all the confeſſion they can make of Reſtraining our Friends, <hi>that they cruelly put them to Death, and <hi>thereby overcame them;</hi>
                  </hi> And it is not known to us, that the Court at <hi>Boſton</hi> hath ſuch <hi>Abſolute Power,</hi> as that the free Subjects of <hi>England</hi> may not come and return <hi>again</hi> and <hi>again,</hi> according to their lawfull occaſions, without leave from the Authority of <hi>Boſton Court;</hi> I ſay, this ſeems to be <hi>uſurped Authority,</hi> rather than lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>eſtabliſhed</hi> upon them by <hi>CHARLES the Firſt,</hi> but it is apparent, and the King knoweth it, that in this caſe the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates of <hi>Boston</hi> have taken <hi>too much upon them,</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded further than they can juſtifie, either <hi>before God,</hi> or <hi>the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169368:8"/> King,</hi> in <hi>Impriſoning, Whipping, cutting off Ears, Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and <hi>putting to Death</hi> the good Subjects of <hi>England,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either <hi>Preſident, Example,</hi> or any <hi>Power</hi> derived from the <hi>Lawful Authority</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And we have cauſe to ſay, They were ſo far from deſiring to ſpare their lives (as they would ſuggeſt to the King) <hi>that they thirſted <hi>for their blood,</hi>
                  </hi> and nothing elſe could ſatisfie them but the extinguiſhment of their lives <hi>by ſhameful tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, The Petitioners fawn and flatter in theſe words; (ſay they) <hi>Let not the King hear Mens words; your ſervants are true Men, fearers of God and the King, and not given to Change; zealous of Government and Order; We are not ſeditious to the Intereſt of Caeſar, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In Anſwer to this, many things are conſiderable:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Why ſhould the Petitioners ſeem to exhort the King, <hi>Not to hear Mens Words?</hi> Shall the Innocent be <hi>accuſed before him,</hi> and not heard in their <hi>Lawful Defence?</hi> Muſt not the King hear the <hi>Accuſed</hi> as well as the <hi>Accuſers,</hi> and in as much Juſtice? I hope God hath given him more Nobility of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, than to receive or put in practice ſuch Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and I deſire it may be far from the King, ever to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn any Perſon or People upon the Accuſation of others, without full hearing of <hi>the Accuſed,</hi> as well as <hi>their Enemies;</hi> for it is <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Equity</hi> ſo to do, and thereby ſhall his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be the more juſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They pretend <hi>to be Servants to the King,</hi> and <hi>that they fear him, and are not given to Change:</hi> I ſhall not ſeem to intrude into the Matters to which I am a ſtranger; but I leave this Caſe to the King to Conſider what their former Actings, and the Current of their Spirit hath been towards the King: I ſhall only inſtance one Particular, well known to me in a Letter to one <hi>Gurden,</hi> dated at <hi>Boſton,</hi> and Subſcribed by ſome of theſe Petitioners; where they ſay, <hi>There is more Danger in theſe</hi> Quakers (as they call them) <hi>to trouble and overcome</hi> England, <hi>than in the King of</hi> Scots, <hi>and all the Popiſh Princes in</hi> Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many: theſe be the Petitioners own words, whereby it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt what the current of their Spirit was againſt the King <hi>then,</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:169368:8"/> though <hi>now</hi> they have changed their Tale, and call Him <hi>High</hi> and <hi>Mighty Prince,</hi> and <hi>Dread Soveraign,</hi> and ſuch like; and that <hi>they are the Kings Servants, &amp;c.</hi> when as not long ſince they have ſignified by their words, quoted againſt them, <hi>That there was Danger in the King of</hi> SCOTS (as they called him) and <hi>reputed him <hi>a Troubler of</hi>
                  </hi> ENGLAND; and <hi>num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred him with <hi>the Popiſh Princes of</hi>
                  </hi> Germany, <hi>or amongst them:</hi> Let but the King Conſider their own words, and he ſhall plainly read as well the temper of their Spirit againſt him not long ſince, as he ſhall ſee <hi>their Hypocriſies</hi> and <hi>fawning flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries</hi> at this time; and he may fully perceive that theſe Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners are given <hi>to Change,</hi> though they would make him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve otherwiſe; And this <hi>their Addreſs</hi> unto the King, is like the approach of the uncircumciſed <hi>Gibeonites</hi> unto <hi>Joſhua,</hi> ch. 9. who wrought <hi>wilily</hi> and <hi>deceitfully,</hi> uſing the ſame words to <hi>Joſhua, We are thy Servants,</hi> as theſe Petitioners have uſed to the King; whoſe deceitful Addreſs is equally parallel with that mentioned: The Caſe is worth obſerving, <hi>Joſhua</hi> 9. verſ. 4, 6, 9.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As <hi>for being Zealous of Government and Order, not Seditious nor Schiſmaticks,</hi> as they ſay, it is to be Conſidered, That their Government, and the Order thereof, is not only <hi>different</hi> and <hi>contrary</hi> to the Goverment and Order of the <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but <hi>different</hi> and <hi>contrary</hi> alſo to the wholſome Conſtitution of the <hi>Civil Government</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> who have made Laws, and executed them <hi>to Baniſhment</hi> and <hi>Death,</hi> without any Power derived from the lawful Authority of <hi>England;</hi> which is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute contrary to their Pattent, by which they Hold their Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, <hi>which ſaith, <hi>They ſhall make no Lawes contrary to the Lawes of</hi>
                  </hi> England, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And I ſhall not Charge them in the Kings Preſence further <hi>of Sedition</hi> and <hi>Schiſm</hi> than Himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth concerning them.</p>
               <p>Again, The Petitioners ſay, <hi>They could not live without the Publick Worſhip of God, and they were not permitted the uſe of Publick Worſhip without ſuch a Yoak, Subſcription and Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as they could not Conſent unto without ſin, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In Anſwer to this, this is to be Conſidered:</p>
               <p>That theſe Petitioners have laid <hi>heavier Yoaks</hi> of <hi>Subſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:169368:9"/> and <hi>Conformity <hi>upon others</hi>
                  </hi> than ever was laid upon <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves;</hi> Witneſs their Impoſing Fines upon ſuch as cannot conform to their Worſhip, ſome <hi>ten ſhillings,</hi> ſome <hi>forty ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings,</hi> and ſome <hi>five pounds;</hi> if any ſhall be abſent from their Aſſembly it is ſo much a day; and if any keep any Meetings different from their Way of Publick Worſhip, it is ſo much a time; and theſe are <hi>unjuſt</hi> and <hi>illegal Impoſitions;</hi> and it is a heinous yoak <hi>of Tyranny</hi> put upon the neck of the Kings good Subjects, without any Power derived in this caſe from the King: This they themſelves do, and yet are Complaining of ſuch <hi>Impoſitions</hi> and <hi>Yoaks</hi> laid upon them <hi>by the Biſhops,</hi> which were not compareable to theſe; which diſcovers their own juſt Condemnation in the ſame Matters for which they Accuſe others.</p>
               <p>And thus theſe CONSIDERATIONS are Preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the King, in Vindication of that Innocent People, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Quakers,</hi> whom theſe Petitioners have Accuſed, as Guilty of heinous Crimes, that themſelves might appear Innocent of the <hi>Cruelty,</hi> and <hi>Injuſtice,</hi> and <hi>ſhedding of the Blood of Iuſt men</hi> without Cauſe; being men of <hi>Guilty Conſciences,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom the Terror of God and of the King, ſeems to be, becauſe of what they have done: But now, let the King rightly Conſider of the Caſe between <hi>Us</hi> and <hi>Them,</hi> and let him not hide his Face from the Hearing of the Cry of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Blood; And for a further Teſtimony of <hi>the Wickedneſs</hi> and <hi>Enmity</hi> of theſe Petitioners, and to Demonſtrate how far they have Proceeded contrary to the <hi>good Lawes</hi> and <hi>Authority of England,</hi> and contrary <hi>to their own Pattent:</hi> Hereunto is Annexed a Breif of their unjuſt Dealings towards the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> (ſo called)</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>E. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="declaration">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:169368:9"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A DECLARATION Of ſome part of the SUFFERINGS of the People of God (in ſcorn called</hi> QUAKERS) <hi>from the Profeſſors in</hi> NEW-ENGLAND, Only for the Exerciſe of their Conſciences to the Lord, and Obeying and Confeſſing to the <hi>TRUTH,</hi> as in his Light he had diſcovered it to them.</head>
               <p n="1">1. TWo Honeſt and Innocent Women <hi>ſtripped ſtark naked,</hi> and ſearched after ſuch <hi>an inhumane man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> as modeſty will not permit particularly to mention.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Twelve Strangers in that Country, but free-born of this Nation, <hi>received twenty three Whippings,</hi> the moſt of them being with a Whip <hi>of three Cords,</hi> with <hi>Knots at the ends,</hi> and laid on with as much ſtrength as they could be by the Arm of their Executioner, the ſtripes amounting to <hi>Three hundred and ſeventy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Eighteen Inhabitants of the Country, being free-born <hi>Engliſh,</hi> received <hi>twenty three Whippings,</hi> the ſtripes amoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to <hi>two hundred and fifty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Sixty four Impriſonments of the Lords People, for their obedience to his Will, amounting to <hi>Five hundred and nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen weeks,</hi> much of it being <hi>very cold weather,</hi> and the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants kept in Priſon <hi>in harveſt time,</hi> which was very much to their loſſe; beſides many more Impriſoned, of which time we cannot give a juſt account.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Two beaten with <hi>Pitched Ropes,</hi> the blows amounting to <hi>an hundred thirty nine,</hi> by which one of them was brought near unto death, much of his body being beat <hi>like unto a jelly,</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:169368:10"/> and one of their own Doctors, a Member of their Church, who ſaw him, ſaid, <hi>It would be a Miracle if ever he recovered, he expecting the fleſh ſhould rot off the bones;</hi> who afterwards was baniſhed upon pain of death. There are many Witneſſes of this there.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Alſo, an Innocent man, an Inhabitant of <hi>Boſton,</hi> they <hi>baniſhed</hi> from his Wife and Children, and put to ſeek a habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in the Winter; and in caſe he returned again, he was to be kept Priſoner during his life: and for returning again, he was put in Priſon, and hath been now a Priſoner above a year.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Twenty five <hi>Baniſhments,</hi> upon the penalties of being <hi>whipt,</hi> or having <hi>their Ears cut;</hi> or <hi>branded in the Hand,</hi> if they returned.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Fines laid upon the Inhabitants for meeting together, and edifying one another, as the Saints ever did; and <hi>for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to ſwear,</hi> it being contrary to Chriſt's Command, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounting to <hi>about a Thouſand pound,</hi> beſides what they have done ſince, that we have not heard of; many Families, in which there are many Children, are almoſt ruined, by theſe unmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful proceedings.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Five kept <hi>Fifteen dayes</hi> (in all) <hi>without food,</hi> and <hi>Fifty eight</hi> dayes ſhut up cloſe by the Jaylor, and had none that he knew of; and from ſome of them he ſtopt up the windows, hindring them from convenient air.</p>
               <p n="10">10. One laid <hi>Neck and Heels</hi> in Irons for <hi>ſixteen hours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. One <hi>very deeply burnt</hi> in the right hand <hi>with the letter</hi> H. after he had been whipt with above <hi>Thirty ſtripes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. One chained the moſt part of Twenty dayes to a Logg of wood in an open Priſon in the Winter-time.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Five Appeals to <hi>England,</hi> denied at <hi>Boſton.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. Three <hi>had their right Ears cut by the Hangman in the Priſon,</hi> the Door being barred, and not a Friend ſuffered to be preſent while it was doing, though ſome much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired it.</p>
               <p n="15">15. One of the Inhabitants of <hi>Salem,</hi> who ſince is baniſhed upon pain of Death, <hi>had one half of his Houſe and Land ſeized on while he was in Priſon,</hi> a month before he knew of it.</p>
               <p n="16">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:169368:10"/>16. At a General Court in <hi>Boſton,</hi> they made an Order, <hi>That thoſe who had not wherewithal to anſwer the Fines that were laid upon them</hi> (for their Conſciences) <hi>ſhould be ſold for Bond-men, and Bond-women to</hi> Barbados, Virginia, <hi>or any of the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Plantations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="17">17. Eighteen of the People of God were at ſeveral times baniſhed <hi>upon pain of Death,</hi> ſix of them were their own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, two of which being very aged people, and well known among their Neighbours to be of honeſt Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, being Baniſhed from their Houſes and Families, and put upon Travelling and other hardſhips, ſoon ended their dayes; whoſe Death we can do no leſſe than charge upon the Rulers of <hi>Boſton,</hi> they being the occaſion of it.</p>
               <p n="18">18. Alſo three of the Servants of the Lord <hi>they put to Death,</hi> all of them for obedience to the Truth, in the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of it againſt the wicked Rulers and Laws at <hi>Boſton.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="19">19. And ſince they have baniſhed four more, <hi>upon pain of Death;</hi> and twenty four of the Inhabitants of <hi>Salem</hi> were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, and more Fines called for, and their Goods ſeized on, to the value of Forty pounds, for meeting together in the fear of God, and ſome for <hi>refuſing to ſwear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe things (O King) from time to time have we pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſuffered, and not for the tranſgreſſion of any Juſt or Righteous Law, either pertaining to the Worſhip of God, or the Civil Government of <hi>England,</hi> but ſimply and barely for our Conſciences to God, of which we can more at large give Thee (or whom thou mayeſt order) a full Account (if Thou wilt let us have admiſſion to Thee, who are <hi>Baniſhed upon pain of Death,</hi> and have had <hi>our Ears cut,</hi> who are, ſome of us, in <hi>England</hi> attending upon Thee) both of the <hi>Cauſes of our Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings,</hi> and <hi>the Manner</hi> of their diſorderly and illegal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding againſt us; Who begun <hi>with Immodeſty,</hi> went on <hi>in Inhumanity</hi> and <hi>Cruelty,</hi> and were not ſatisfied until <hi>they had the Blood of three of the Martyrs of</hi> JESUS: Revenge for all which we do not ſeek, but lay them before Thee, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering Thou haſt been well acquainted with Sufferings, and ſo mayeſt the better conſider them that ſuffer, and mayeſt for the future reſtrain the Violence of theſe Rulers of <hi>New-England,</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:169368:11"/> having Power in Thy hands; they being but the Children of the Family, of which Thou art Chief Ruler; Who have in divers of their Proceedings <hi>forfeited their Patent;</hi> as upon a ſtrict Inquiry in many particulars will appear.</p>
               <p>And this, O King, we are aſſured of, that in time to come it will not repent Thee, if by a <hi>Cloſe Rebuke</hi> Thou ſtoppeſt the <hi>Bloody Proceedings</hi> of theſe <hi>Bloody Perſecutors;</hi> for in ſo doing, Thou wilt engage the hearts of many honeſt Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple unto Thee, both there and here; and for ſuch Works of Mercy, the Bleſſing is obtained, and ſhewing it, is the way to proſper.</p>
               <p>We are Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of theſe things; Who,
<list>
                     <item>Beſides long Impriſonments, and many cruel Whippings, <hi>Had our Ears cut,</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Rous,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Copeland.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Beſides many long Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, divers cruel Whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings, with the ſeizing on our Goods, are Baniſhed <hi>upon pain of Death,</hi> and ſome of us do wait here in <hi>England,</hi> and deſire that we may have an Order to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn in Peace to our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies,
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Samuel Shattock.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Joſiah Southick.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Nicholas Phelps.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Joſeph Nicholſon.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Jane Nicholſon.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="relation">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:169368:11"/>
               <head>Here follovveth a brief Relation of the Bloody Sentence of Death, paſſed on Three of the Servants of the Lord, by <hi>John Endicot;</hi> viz. <hi>William Robinſon, Marmaduke Stevenſon,</hi> and <hi>Mary Dyar;</hi> And alſo the Manner of their Execution at <hi>Boſton</hi> in <hi>New-England.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVIlliam Robinſon</hi> and <hi>Marmaduke Stevenſon,</hi> two Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Lord, called <hi>Quakers,</hi> were impriſoned in <hi>Boſton</hi> in <hi>New-England;</hi> and at the beginning of the 7th Month, 59. they were called before the Court of <hi>Aſſiſtance,</hi> by whom they bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h were Sentenced to be Baniſhed upon pain of Death; yet notwithſtanding the Sentence aforeſaid, they made a <hi>Decree</hi> to have <hi>William Robinſon</hi> whipt, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Conſtable to get an able man to do it; which thing being accompliſhed, they cauſed <hi>William Robinſon</hi> to be brought into the open Street, and there ſtript him; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving put his Hands through the holes of a Carriage of a great Gun, where the Goaler (a Member of their Church) held him till the Executioner gave him <hi>twenty</hi> ſtripes with a Three-fold Cord-whip, with Knots at the ends; which ſtripes were laid on in a violent manner, according to the Deſire of ſome of the <hi>Blood-thirſty Rulers,</hi> who commanded him to be Whipt ſeverely; whereupon he, together with his fellow-Sufferer, <hi>M. S.</hi> were ſhortly after Releaſed: Yet it being laid upon them from the Lord not to depart that Juriſdiction, they in obedience thereunto paſſed abroad, and had great Service for the Lord within the Juriſdiction aforeſaid, many being by them convinced of the Evil of their wayes; for the Power and Preſence of the Lord of Life was with them to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding of their Enemies.</p>
               <p>And upon the 13th of the 8th Month, it being upon them ſo to do, they Returned again <hi>to Boſton,</hi> where they, with ſeven other Friends, were Apprehended, and caſt all of them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Priſon: But <hi>William Robinſon</hi> and <hi>Marmaduke Stevenſon</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:169368:12"/> were delivered to the Cuſtody of the Goaler to be kept <hi>in Chains</hi> in a Room by themſelves, which accordingly was done, and they had <hi>Chains</hi> laid upon <hi>their Right Leggs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the next Week, on the 20th of the 8th Month, 1659: <hi>William Robinſon, Marmaduke Stevenſon,</hi> and <hi>Mary Dyar</hi> of <hi>Rhode Iſland,</hi> were had into the Court, where <hi>John Endicot,</hi> with others of the <hi>Council,</hi> were Aſſembled; And being called to the <hi>Bar, John Endicot</hi> Commanded the Keeper <hi>to pull off their Hats,</hi> which accordingly was done: Then <hi>John Endicot</hi> began to ſpeak unto them very faintly, as a man poſſeſſed with much fear, in theſe words, <hi>That they had made ſeveral Lawes, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tryed and endeavoured by ſeveral wayes to keep them (<hi>i. e.</hi>
                  </hi> the <hi>Quakers) <hi>from amongſt them; and neither Whipping, nor Impriſoning, nor Cutting off Ears, nor Baniſhing upon pain of Death, would not keep them from amongſt them:</hi>
                  </hi> And further ſaid, <hi>He or They deſired not the Death of any of them:</hi> Yet notwithſtanding, his following words were, <hi>Give eare and hearken to your Sentence of Death;</hi> which words (as was ſaid before) paſſed from him very faintly. Then <hi>William Robinſon</hi> deſired that he might give them an Accompt of the <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> why after Baniſhment upon pain of Death, they ſtayed in their Juriſdiction: But <hi>John Endicot</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing filled with fury, would not permit it to be done; but ſoon after in Envy called <hi>W. R.</hi> by his Name, and ſaid unto him, <hi>Hearken to your Sentence of Death: William Robinſon,</hi> this is your Sentence, <hi>You ſhall be had back to the place from whence you came, &amp; from thence to the place of Execution, to be hanged on the Gallows till you are dead;</hi> And then ſoon after the Goaler was called <hi>to have him away;</hi> which accordingly was done.</p>
               <p>Soon after <hi>William Robinſon</hi> was taken out of the Court; his dear Brother and fellow-Sufferer, <hi>Marmaduke Stevenſon</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſent; The Governour being partial, ſpoke unto him, ſaying, <hi>If you have any thing to ſay, you may ſpeak;</hi> but he was ſilent and gave no Anſwer: whereupon Sentence was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt him alſo in theſe words, <hi>You ſhall be had to the place from whence ye came, and from thence to the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, and there to be Hanged till you are Dead:</hi> Whereupon theſe words were uttered forth by <hi>M. Stevenſon, Give ear ye</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:169368:12"/> Magiſtrates, <hi>and all who are</hi> Guilty, <hi>for this the Lord hath ſaid concerning you, who will perform his Promiſe upon you, That ſame Day you put his Servants to Death, ſhall the Day of</hi> your Viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>paſs over your Heads,</hi> and <hi>you ſhall be</hi> Curſed <hi>for evermore, The mouth of the Lord of Hoſts hath ſpoken it: Therefore in love to you all, take Warning before it be too late, that ſo the Curſe may be removed; for aſſuredly, if you put us to Death, you will bring Innocent Blood upon your own heads, and ſwift deſtruction will come upon you:</hi> After which words were ſpoken, he was had to Priſon again to his Brother <hi>W. Robinſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The like Sentence was alſo paſſed againſt <hi>Mary Dyar,</hi> (after they were taken away) by <hi>John Endicot,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>Mary Dyar, <hi>You ſhall go to the place from whence you came, namely the Priſon, and from thence to the place of Execution, and there to be Hanged until you are Dead:</hi>
                  </hi> Whereupon ſhe made Anſwer, <hi>The Will of the Lord be done.</hi> Then Command was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Marſhal <hi>to take her away;</hi> ſhe returned Anſwer, <hi>Yea, and joyfully I go:</hi> And in her Paſſage to the Priſon ſhe often uſed Speeches <hi>of Praiſe to the Lord for the ſame;</hi> and ſpoke to the Marſhal <hi>to let her go alone, for ſhe would go to the Priſon without him:</hi> The Marſhal Anſwered, <hi>I believe you Mris Dyar,</hi> but <hi>I muſt do what I am Commanded.</hi> This is a ſhort and true Relation of the Sentence paſſed upon them, not for evil-doing, but only for bearing their Teſtimony <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gainſt all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Wickedneſs, and teſtifying to the Truth as it is in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, keeping their Conſciences clear both towards God and Man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="relation">
               <head>Novv Concerning the <hi>Martyrdom</hi> of theſe Three Servants of the Lord, I ſhall give a ſhort and true Relation.</head>
               <p>The 27th day of the ſame Month, was the day appointed that they were to be Executed, having notice thereof given them the Night before, which accordingly was done; For on the 27th day, being the 5th day of the Week, in the latter part thereof, after their Lecture (ſo called) was done; <hi>William Robinſon</hi> and <hi>Marmaduke Stevenſon</hi> were had forth of the Priſon into the open Street, where <hi>James Oliver</hi> was Captain
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:169368:13"/> over a Band of Armed Men, by information 200. which were prepared to Guard them to, and at the place of Execution, with <hi>Drums,</hi> and <hi>Colours,</hi> and <hi>Halberds, Guns, Swords, Pikes, &amp;c.</hi> beſides many <hi>Horſemen</hi> to keep off the Multitude of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: The two dear Lambs being placed near the hinder part, the <hi>chief Marſhal</hi> and <hi>Drummer</hi> next before them; Then Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand being given <hi>to march to the Place of Execution, W. Robin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> ſpake theſe words ſaying, <hi>This is your Hour and the power of Darkneſs;</hi> Then the <hi>Drummer</hi> made a Noiſe with his Drum, and ſhortly ceaſed again; Then <hi>Marmaduke Steven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> ſaid, <hi>This is the Day of your Viſitation, wherein the Lord hath viſited you:</hi> Other words being ſpoke not underſtood by reaſon of the ſound of the Drum: So they walked along in pure retired Chearfulneſs to the Place of Execution, triumph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the ſtrength of the Lamb, over all the wrath of man, and fury of the Beaſt, in the pure retired Heavenly Dominion of the Inviſible God. And when they came to the Ladders-foot, <hi>they took their leave each of other;</hi> and <hi>William Robinſon</hi> ſtept up the Ladder, and ſpake to the People, ſaying, <hi>This is the Day of your Viſitation wherein the Lord hath viſited you; This is the Day the Lord is Riſen in his Mighty Power to be Avenged on all his Adverſaries:</hi> And the Rope being about his Neck, as he ſpake, the Executioner bound his Hands and Leggs; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> his Neck-cloth being tyed about his Face, he ſaid, <hi>Now ye are made Manifeſt:</hi> So the Executioner being about to turn him off the Ladder, he ſaid, <hi>I Suffer for Chriſt, in whom I live, and for whom I die.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So he being turned off, <hi>Marmaduke Stevenſon</hi> went up the Ladder, and ſpake to the People, ſaying, <hi>Be it known unto all this Day, that we Suffer not as Evil-Doers, but for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake;</hi> And as the Executioner was about to turn him off, theſe words he expreſſed, <hi>This Day ſhall we be at Reſt with the Lord.</hi> Thus the faithful Witneſſes ſealed their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony for the Lord againſt the Dragons Power, and bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly departed with Praiſes in their mouths, entering joyfully with their Beloved into Everlaſting Reſt.</p>
               <p>This Accompt was ſent from <hi>Plimouth</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> by <hi>Peter Peirſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:169368:13"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mary Dyar</hi> having received the ſame Sentence, only for coming a ſecond time to <hi>Boſton</hi> to viſit her impriſoned Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren there, was with them carried to the place of Execution; and after they two were executed, ſhe ſtept up the Ladder, and had her Coats tyed about her feet, and the Rope put about her neck; and as the Hangman was ready to turn her off, they cryed out, <hi>Stop, for ſhe was Reprieved,</hi> and having looſed her feet, bad her come down; but ſhe was not forward to come down, but ſtood ſtill, ſaying, <hi>She was there willing to ſuffer, as her Brethren did, unleſs they would null their wicked Law;</hi> but they pulled her down, and a day or two after carried her by force out of Town.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Here followeth the Copy of a Letter that <hi>Mary Dyar</hi> ſent to the Rulers of <hi>Boſton,</hi> after ſhe had received the Sentence of Death.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>To the General Court now in</hi> Boſton.</head>
               <p>VVHereas I am by many charged with the guiltineſſe of my own Blood; if you mean in my coming to <hi>Boſton,</hi> I am therein clear, and juſtified by the Lord, in whoſe Will I came, who will require my Blood of you be ſure; who have made a Law to take away the Lives of the Innocent Servants of God, if they come among you, who are called by you, <hi>Curſed Quakers;</hi> although I ſay, and am a living Witneſſe for them and the Lord, that he hath bleſſed them, and ſent them unto you: therefore be not found fighters againſt God, but let my Counſel and Requeſt be accepted with you, To repeal all ſuch Laws, that the Truth and Servants of the Lord may have free paſſage among you, and you kept from ſhedding Innocent Blood, which I know there are many among you would not do, if they knew it ſo to be: nor can the Enemy that ſtirreth you up thus to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy this holy Seed, in any meaſure countervail the great Dammage that you will by thus doing procure: Therefore, ſeeing the Lord hath not hid it from me, it lyeth upon me, in love to your Souls, thus to perſwade you: I have no ſelf-ends, the Lord knoweth, for if my Life were freely granted by you, it would not avail me, nor
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:169368:14"/> could I expect it of you, ſo long as I ſhould daily hear or ſee the Sufferings of theſe People, my dear Brethren, and Seed, with whom my Life is bound up, as I have done theſe two years; and now it is like to encreaſe, even unto death, for no evil doing, but coming among you: Was ever the like Laws heard of among a People that profeſs Chriſt come in the fleſh? And have ſuch no other wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons but ſuch Laws, to fight againſt <hi>Spiritual Wickedneſs</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, as you call it? Wo is me for you! of whom take you Counſel? ſearch with the Light of Chriſt in ye, and it will ſhew you of whom, as it hath done me and many more, who have been diſobedient and deceived, as now you are; which Light as you come into, and obeying what is made manifeſt to you therein, you will not repent, that you were kept from ſhedding Blood, though it were from a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: It's not mine own Life I ſeek, <hi>(for I chuſe rather to ſuffer with the People of God, than to enjoy the Pleaſures of Egypt)</hi> but the Life of the Seed, which I know the Lord hath bleſſed; and therefore ſeeks the Enemy thus vehemently the Life thereof to deſtroy, as in all Ages he ever did: Oh hearken not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him I beſeech you, for the Seeds ſake, which is one in all, and is dear in the ſight of God; which they that touch, touch the Apple of his Eye, and cannot eſcape his Wrath, whereof I having felt, cannot but perſwade all men that I have to do withal, especially you who name the Name of Chriſt, <hi>to depart from ſuch Iniquity,</hi> as <hi>ſhedding Blood even of the Sain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s of the Moſt High;</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let my Requeſt have as much acceptance with you (if you be Chriſtians) as <hi>Eſther</hi> had with <hi>Ahaſueras,</hi> (whoſe relation is ſhort of that that's between Chriſtians) and my Requeſt is the ſame that hers was; and he ſaid not, that he had made a Law, and it would be diſhonourable for him to revoke it, but when he underſtood that theſe People were ſo prized by her, and ſo nearly concerned her, (as in truth theſe are to me) as you may ſee what he did for her; Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I leave theſe Lines with you, appealing to the faithful and true Witneſſe of God, which is One in all Conſciences, before whom we muſt all appear; with whom I ſhall eternally reſt, in everlaſting Joy and Peace, whether you will hear or forbear: with Him is my Reward, with whom to live is my Joy, and to dye is my Gain, though I had not had your forty eight hours warning, for the preparation to the Death of <hi>Mary Dyar.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:169368:14"/>
               <p>And know this alſo, That if through the Enmity you ſhall declare your ſelves worſe than <hi>Ahaſuerus,</hi> and confirm your Law, though it were but by taking away the Life of one of us, That the Lord will overthrow both your Law and you, by his Righteous Judgements and Plagues powred juſtly upon you, who now whilſt you are Warned thereof, and tenderly ſought unto, may avoid the one by removing the other: If you neither hear nor obey the Lord nor his Servants, yet will he ſend more of his Servants among you, ſo that your end ſhall be fruſtrated, that think to reſtrain them, you call Curſed <hi>Quakers,</hi> from coming among you by any thing you can do to them; yea verily, he hath a Seed here among you, for whom we have ſuffered all this while, and yet ſuffer; whom the Lord of the Harveſt will ſend forth more Labourers to gather (out of the mouths of the Devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of all ſorts) into his Fold, where he will lead them into freſh Paſtures, even the paths of Righteouſneſs for his Names ſake: Oh! let none of you put this good day far from you, which verily in the Light of the Lord I ſee approaching, even to many in and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Boſton,</hi> which is the bittereſt and darkeſt Profeſſing place, and ſo to continue ſo long as you have done, that ever I heard of; let the time paſt therefore ſuffice, for ſuch a Profeſſion as brings forth ſuch Fruits as theſe Lawes are. In Love and in the Spirit of Meekneſs I again beſeech you, for I have no Enmity to the Perſons of any; but you ſhall know, That God will not be mocked, but what you ſow, that ſhall ye reap from him, that will render to every one according to the deeds done in the body, whether good or evil; Even ſo be it, ſaith</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Mary Dyar.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>
                  <hi>A Copy of this was given to the General Court after</hi> Mary Dyar <hi>had received the Sentence of</hi> Death, <hi>about the 8th or 9th Month, 1659.</hi>
               </trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>A further Accompt concerning <hi>Mary Dyars</hi> Martyrdom.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MAry Dyar</hi> being freed, as aforeſaid, returned to <hi>Road-Iſland,</hi> and afterwards to <hi>Long-Iſland,</hi> and there was
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:169368:15"/> moſt part of the Winter, over the <hi>Iſland,</hi> where ſhe had good Service for the Lord; and then came to <hi>Shelter-Iſland,</hi> (whence ſhe thought ſhe might paſs to <hi>Road-Iſland</hi>) and being there, ſometime ſhe had Movings from the Lord, to go to <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton,</hi> and there ſhe came the 21 of the 3d Month, 1660. and the 30th day was their Governour Choſen, and the 31 of the 3d Month, in the former part of the day, ſhe was ſent for to the General Court; The Governour ſaid, <hi>Are ye the ſame</hi> Mary Dyar <hi>that was here before?</hi> (ſpeaking of one in <hi>Old-England</hi> that Returned, and would have made them believe he was not the ſame man; with more words to that purpoſe, and ſaid, <hi>Have not you ſuch Evaſions?</hi>) Mary Dyar, <hi>I am the ſame</hi> Mary Dyar <hi>that was here the laſt General Court.</hi> The Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour ſaid, <hi>You will own your ſelf a</hi> Quaker, <hi>will you not?</hi> M.D. <hi>I own my ſelf to be ſo reproachfully called.</hi> The bloody-minded Goaler having now opportunity to have his blood-thirſty Will fulfilled, ſaid, <hi>She is a Vagabond.</hi> The Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor ſaid, <hi>The Sentence was paſſed upon her the laſt General Court,</hi> and <hi>now likewiſe; <hi>You muſt Return to the Priſon from whence you came, and there Remain un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>il to Morrow at Nine of the Clock, then from thence you muſt go to the Gallows, and there be Hanged till you are Dead.</hi>
                  </hi> Mary Dyar ſaid, <hi>This is no more than that thou ſaidſt before: <hi>I, I,</hi>
                  </hi> (the Governour ſaid) <hi>and now it is to be Executed,</hi> therefore <hi>prepare your ſelf to Morrow at Nine of the Clock</hi> (being the firſt day of the 4th Month, 1660) <hi>Mary Dyar</hi> Anſwered and ſaid, <hi>I came in Obedience to the Will of God the laſt General Court, deſiring you to Repeal your unrighteous Lawes of Baniſhment upon pain of Death; and that ſame is my work now, and eaneſt Requeſt, becauſe ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed before to grant my Requeſt, although I told you, That if ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to Repeal them, the Lord will ſend others of his Servants to Witneſs againſt them. John Endicot</hi> asked her, <hi>Whether ſhe was a Prophet?</hi> She ſaid, <hi>She ſpake the words that the Lord ſpake in her; and now the thing is come to paſs:</hi> She beginning to ſpeak of her Call, <hi>J. Endicot</hi> ſaid, <hi>Away with her, away with her:</hi> So ſhe was brought to the Priſon-Houſe, where ſhe was before, cloſe ſhut up, until the next day. About the time perfixt, the Marſhal <hi>Michaelſon</hi> came and called <hi>haſtily</hi> for her; when he
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:169368:15"/> came into the Room, ſhe deſired him <hi>to ſtay a little;</hi> and ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mildly to him, ſhe ſaid, <hi>She ſhould be ready preſently;</hi> even like a Sheep prepared for the ſlaughter: But he in the Wolviſh Nature, ſaid, <hi>He could not wait upon her, but ſhe ſhould now wait upon him. Margaret Smith,</hi> her Companion, hearing him ſpeak theſe words, with others, from the <hi>Cain</hi>-like Spirit, was moved to Teſtifie againſt their unjuſt Lawes and Proceedings, being grieved to ſee both him, and many others, in ſuch groſſe Darkneſs and Hard-heartedneſs: Then he ſaid, <hi>You ſhall have your ſhare of the ſame,</hi> with other violent words. Then they brought her forth, and <hi>Drums</hi> were beat <hi>before</hi> and <hi>behind her</hi> with a Band of Souldiers through the Town, and ſo to the Place of Execution, which is about a Mile, the <hi>Drums beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> that none might hear her ſpeak all the way.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>The Words of <hi>Mary Dyar</hi> upon the Ladder.</head>
               <p>Some ſaid unto her, <hi>That if ſhe would return, ſhe might come down and ſave her L fe (<hi>Bonner</hi>
                  </hi> and <hi>Gardener</hi>-like.) She anſwered and ſaid, <hi>Nay, I cannot, for in obedience to the Will of the Lord God I came; and in his Will I abide faithful to the Death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Their Captain, <hi>John Webb,</hi> ſaid, ſhe had been here before, and had the Sentence of Baniſhment upon pain of Death; and had broken this Law in coming again now, as well as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and therefore ſhe was guilty of her own Blood.</p>
               <p>To which <hi>M. Dyar</hi> ſaid, <hi>Nay, I came to keep Blood-guilti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs from you, deſiring you to repeal the unrighteous &amp; unjuſt Law of Baniſhment upon pain of Death; made againſt the Innocent Servants of the Lord: therefore my Blood will be required at your hands, who wilfully do it: but for thoſe that do it in the ſimplicity of their hearts, I do deſire the Lord to forgive them. I came to do the Will of my Father, and in obedience to his Will, I ſtand even to the Death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Wilſon,</hi> their Prieſt of <hi>Boſton</hi> ſaid, M. <hi>Dyar, O Repent, O Repent, and be not ſo deluded and carried away by the deceit of the Devil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>M. Dyar</hi> anſwered and ſaid, <hi>Nay, man, I am not now to Repent.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:169368:16"/>
               <p>Some asked her, <hi>Whether ſhe would have the Elders to pray for her?</hi> She ſaid, <hi>I know never an Elder here.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They asked, <hi>Whether ſhe would have any of the People to pray for her?</hi> She ſaid, <hi>She deſired the Prayers of all the People of God.</hi> Some ſcoffingly ſaid, <hi>It may be ſhe thinks there is none here, this is a mock. M. Dyar</hi> looked about and ſaid, <hi>I know but few here.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then they ſpake to her again, <hi>That one of the Elders might pray for her.</hi> She replyed, and ſaid, <hi>Nay, firſt a Child, then a young man, then a ſtrong man, before an Elder of Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some charged her with ſomething that was not underſtood what it was. But her Anſwer was, <hi>It's falſe, it's falſe, I never ſpoke the words.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then one ſaid, ſhe ſhould ſay, <hi>ſhe had been in Paradiſe.</hi> And ſhe anſwered, <hi>Yea, I have been in Paradiſe ſeveral dayes.</hi> And more ſhe ſpake of her Eternal Happineſs, that's out of mind. And ſo ſweetly and chearfully in the Lord ſhe finiſhed her Teſtimony, and dyed a <hi>faithful Martyr of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſtill they are going on in acting their cruel Laws; for the ſame day, in the former part of it, they ſent for <hi>Joſeph Nicholſon,</hi> and his Wife <hi>Jane Nicholſon, <hi>and baniſhed them on pain of Death.</hi>
                  </hi> Then ſent for three more, and whileſt they were examining them, there came one to the Court, and tells them, <hi>Now M. Dyar is caſt off.</hi> Then ſeveral of the Court ſpake to this purpoſe, and one ſcoffingly ſaid, <hi>She did hang as a Flag for them to take example by. <hi>[But precious in the ſight of the Lord is the Death of his Saints.]</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now the fruits of <hi>New-England</hi> Profeſſors are made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to the World, who are ſo far degenerated from the Lord, that they ſet up the killing of his Saints, <hi>as an Euſign,</hi> or <hi>a Flag,</hi> that many may follow their Cruelty. Theſe are the people that ſay, <hi>Their Churches are the pureſt Churches in the World;</hi> and <hi>that their Magiſtrates, are godly Magiſtrates,</hi> and <hi>godly Miniſters:</hi> A fair ſhew to the World; even another <hi>Beaſt coming up out of the Earth; and he had two horns, like a Lamb; and he ſpake as a Dragon; and he exerciſeth all the power of the firſt Beaſt before him.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:169368:16"/>
               <p>And their General Court being ended, they left Nine of us ſtill remaining in Priſon (it ſeems) looking for encouragement from <hi>England,</hi> that more may follow their <hi>Enſign.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And we have a further Accompt alſo, That one of our Friends, named <hi>William Leddra,</hi> being Baniſhed upon pain of Death; he not Departing the Colony, but being moved to Return again to <hi>Boſton,</hi> was Apprehended and caſt into Priſon, and there lyeth Chained to a Logg with a Horſe-lock, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to Die.</p>
               <p>By all which it is manifeſt, That in them is fulfilled the words of Chriſt, <hi>He that will loſe his life for my ſake, ſhall find it:</hi> But we do clearly in the Light of the Lord ſee, That <hi>he that ſeeks to ſave his own life, will kill the Juſt:</hi> Witneſs what theſe Perſecutors in <hi>New-England</hi> (who fled to ſave themſelves) have done.</p>
               <p>Therefore let all People take notice, That Chriſt, nor his Apoſtles, never gave any Preſident, Example or Command, to take away the Lives of any: Who ended the <hi>Jews</hi> Law, which was to put to death falſe Prophets and Blaſphemers; and ſo all that be in the Power of God, may ſee the <hi>Ignorance</hi> of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of <hi>New-England,</hi> concerning the Scriptures and the Power of God, who know not what ſpirit they are of.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>POST-SCRIPT.</head>
               <p>LEt the King hear me <hi>one Requeſt</hi> more, which I crave of him, and (I hope) will be judged but juſt in me to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede for, and noble juſt and righteous in him to grant.</p>
               <p>Foraſmuch as I perceive, that divers Informations and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations againſt us, may come to the Kings Ear, by Word, or Letter, or Petition, whereby our Innocent Cauſe may be falſly reputed, and we made to ſeem great Offenders in his preſence; upon which I Requeſt, That we may have the knowledge of what any <hi>ſuch Informations</hi> and <hi>Accuſations</hi> are againſt us in any relation, and who are <hi>our Accuſers;</hi> and this is requiſite for us to <hi>know,</hi> and juſt in the King <hi>to grant,</hi> that we may not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer prejudice or ſuſpition in the Kings mind in any caſe, and neither know <hi>what our Accuſations,</hi> nor whom the <hi>Accuſers
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:169368:17"/> are;</hi> And therefore we ſhould account it great favour in the King, and no more than what he may do <hi>in Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> to ſuffer us to have the knowledge <hi>of what we are Accuſed of,</hi> in any <hi>caſe,</hi> in any <hi>manner,</hi> by any <hi>perſon;</hi> and this for no other end, than that we m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y make <hi>our Innocent</hi> and <hi>Lawful De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,</hi> and may clear our ſelves from all falſe Accuſations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King, and all the world; that we may not be judged in any matter upon any <hi>ſecret Information</hi> and <hi>Accuſation,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being heard in our lawful Defence; for if the King ſhould ſo proceed in Judgment againſt us, upon any Accuſation, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hearing our <hi>Defence,</hi> as well as our Accuſers <hi>Charge,</hi> how ſhould he but endanger himſelf in paſſing unrighteous Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt us to his own hurt: And therefore that the King may be truly directed to juſt Judgment, by hearing <hi>the Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>in their Defence,</hi>
                  </hi> as well as the <hi>Accuſers <hi>in their Charge;</hi>
                  </hi> and that Gods People, and his glorious Truth, may not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly judged without hearing their <hi>Defence,</hi> and for the avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of unjuſt Judgment and Perſecution in the Land, and for the reproving of falſe Accuſers; for theſe Cauſes the King ought to ſhew ſo much favour and juſtice, to let us know what our Accuſations are, and by whom, in all things that are or may be preſented to him; for there is not any thing, whereof we can be accuſed, concerning either Civil or Religious Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, but I hope we can make <hi>our Defence clear,</hi> and prove <hi>Gods Innocency,</hi> with which we are cloathed, from <hi>all falſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations</hi> and <hi>Accuſations;</hi> And this Requeſt I preſent to the King, and not preſumptuouſly, but with all due reſpect to the honour of God, and love to his People, and Reverence to the King.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>E. B.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>London</hi>
                     <date>the 15th of the firſt <hi>Month,</hi> 1660.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
